Guide to the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas papers
1837-1961
YCAL MSS 76
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
93
(173 boxes) + artwork, objects, cold storage
The Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers contain manuscripts of writings, letters, clippings, photographs, artworks, and personal papers relating to the life and work of Gertrude Stein and her companion, Alice B. Toklas, and to Gertrude's brother, Leo Stein, an artist and writer. As well as holding the bulk of Stein's literary output (often described as "experimental" or "cubist" writing), the materials document Stein and Toklas' involvement with the literary and art scene in Paris during the first half of the 20th century. Series I, Writings, contains holograph and typescript drafts of the majority of Gertrude Stein's writings, including "The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas," "The Making of Americans" (complete with a quantity of notes, or "studies"), "Tender Buttons" and a group of unpublished fragments and carnets, notebooks kept by Stein with preliminary drafts of writings. Series II, Correspondence of Gertrude Stein, contains letters sent from a wide variety of Stein's friends: artists such as Georges Bracque, Jean Cocteau, and Pablo Picasso; writers such as Sherwood Anderson, Ernest Hemingway, and Thornton Wilder; and acquaintances through many years such as Mildred Aldrich, Etta and Claribel Cone, Robert Haas, Mabel Dodge Luhan,Sir Francis Rose, Virgil Thomson, and Carl Van Vechten. Series III, Third Party Letters and Series IV, Alice B. Toklas Correspondence, contain letters from many of the same people, the latter group containing Alice Toklas's correspondence following Gertrude Stein's death. Series V, Personal Papers, and Series VI, Clippings, gather together various personal affects of Stein and Toklas as well as documentation of Stein's life as reported during her lifetime. Series VII, Photographs, show Stein from early childhood through 1946, the year she died. Prints showing Alice Toklas, various friends, artworks, and locales are included in this series, as are several volumes of prints made by Carl Van Vechten. Series VIII and IX contain numerous artworks and objects given by Stein and Toklas. Included here are a painting by Pablo Picasso and a sketch by Henri Matisse.
Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Gertrude Stein, 1946, with subsequent gifts from Alice B. Toklas, ca. 1946-67.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in box 173 and cold storage may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Painting in folder 4273: Restricted. On permanent loan to the Yale University Art Gallery. For more information please consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Collection (YCAL MSS 77) and Leo Stein Collection (YCAL MSS 78).
GERTRUDE STEIN (1874-1946) AND ALICE B. TOKLAS (1877-1967)
The lives of Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas have been documented in detail in numerous books, including The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas, Stein's own account of their early years in Paris. The following is a brief timeline pinpointing key events in their lives:
1874 February 3 Gertrude Stein is born in Allegheny, Pennsylvania. The youngest of Amelia and Daniel Stein's five children, her closest sibling is her brother Leo, born in 1872; other siblings are Michael, born 1865, Simon, born 1867, and Bertha, born 1870.
1875 Stein family moves to Vienna, Austria. April 30 Alice Babette Toklas born in San Francisco, California.
1878 Stein family moves to Paris.
1879 Stein family returns to North America, eventually settling in Oakland, California, where Gertrude will attend school.
1888 Amelia Stein dies.
1890 Toklas family moves to Seattle, Washington, returning several years later to San Francisco.
1891 Daniel Stein dies; Michael, the oldest sibling, takes charge of the family's affairs.
1892 Gertrude Stein moves to Baltimore, Maryland, to live with an aunt.
1893 Gertrude Stein moves to Cambridge, Massachusetts, to enroll in the Harvard Annex (later known as Radcliffe College), to be near her brother, Leo, who is matriculating at Harvard University.
1895 Leo Stein makes trip around the world with his cousin Fred Stein.
1896 Gertrude travels to Europe to meet Leo, returning to America in the fall to enroll at Johns Hopkins Medical School. She earns a B.A. in medicine in 1898, but leaves the graduate program in 1902.
1902-03 Gertrude Stein travels to Europe, ending up in London with her brother Leo. Eventually, she returns to North America, to New York City briefly, before going again to Paris, where Leo is already living.
1903-07 Gertrude and Leo Stein establish a household in Paris at 27 rue de Fleurus, where she begins to write in earnest. They begin collecting artworks, eventually dedicating themselves to a group of young artists, including Henri Matisse and Pablo Picasso. During the winter of 1905-06, Gertrude Stein sits for Picasso's celebrated portrait.
1907 Alice Toklas travels to Paris, meeting Gertrude Stein at 27 rue de Fleurus on Sunday, September 8.
1908 Gertrude and Leo join Michael Stein's family at the Villa Bardi in Fiesole. Alice Toklas sojourns at the nearby Casa Ricci. Gertrude and Alice declare a marriage.
1908-09 Gertrude arranges for the publication of Three Lives in North America by the Grafton Press.
1912-13 Gertrude and Alice vacation in Spain.
1913 The growing rift between Leo and Gertrude is finalized when Leo moves to Settignano, Italy, with his lover Nina Auzias, after several years of living with Gertrude and Alice at 27 rue de Fleurus.
1914 March Tender Buttons is published in New York.
1914 Summer-Fall Gertrude and Alice visit London, staying longer than they expect due to the beginning of the First World War.
1915-16 Gertrude and Alice vacation in Majorca, Spain.
1917-18 Gertrude and Alice work for war relief efforts in France, traveling the countryside in their Ford van.
1920-30 Gertrude continues writing, gradually adding to her growing published bibliography. She and Alice cultivate a circle of friends, creating a literary and artistic salon peopled with writers, artists, entertainers, and American expatriates. The two begin to spend their summers in the South of France, staying at the Hotel Pernollet in Belley and eventually renting a house in Bilignin.
1927 Alice cuts Gertrude's hair.
1929 A poodle named Basket enters the household, the first in a series of dogs to be adopted by Stein and Toklas.
1930 Gertrude and Alice establish the Plain Edition imprint to publish Gertrude's works systematically, beginning with Lucy Church Amiably.
1932 Gertrude writes The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas, which, when published in North America in 1933, becomes a surprise best-seller.
1934 February 8 Four Saint in Three Acts, an opera to be sung, originally written in collaboration with Virgil Thomson in the late 1920s, has its debut at the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford, Connecticut.
1934 October 24 Gertrude and Alice arrive in New York for an extended visit and lecture tour (lasting until Spring, 1935). Their itinerary takes them from Wisconsin to Louisiana, with many long stops in between at Chicago, Virginia, and New York, and a final return to Gertrude's hometown of Oakland.
1936 Gertrude and Alice fly to England, where Gertrude delivers lectures at Cambridge and Oxford.
1937 November Gertrude and Alice move from rue de Fleurus to 5 rue Christine after their landlord reclaims their flat.
1940 June 14 Paris is taken by Germans forces. Gertrude and Alice stay in the South of France.
1940-44 Living at first in their rented homes in Bilignin, Gertrude and Alice move in the winter of 1942 to nearby Culoz. Gertrude continues writing, though they experience times of deprivation and external communications dwindle to practically nil for a time.
1944 December Following the liberation of Paris, Gertrude and Alice move home to find their apartment and their collection of artworks intact.
1945 June Gertrude and Alice tour Germany with American GIs.
1946 July 27 After a brief illness and days after receiving copies of Brewsie and Willie, her final book, Gertrude Stein dies of cancer at the American Hospital at Neuilly.
1946 October 22 Gertrude Stein is buried in Père Lachaise cemetery, Paris, France.
1947 July 29 Leo Stein dies.
1946-67 Alice B. Toklas remains in Paris, dedicating herself to seeing through the publication of The Yale Edition of the Unpublished Writings of Gertrude Stein (issued in eight volumes between 1951 and 1958.) She, herself, begins to write, publishing a volume of memoirs and two cookbooks.
1967 March 7 Shortly before her 90th birthday, Alice Toklas dies in Paris, and is interred next to Gertrude Stein in the tomb in Père Lachaise.
History of the Papers
The story of how Gertrude Stein's papers made their way into the Yale Collection of American Literature has been detailed in an essay by Donald Gallup in the Yale Library Gazette (October 1947). The acquisition of the Stein archive came about in large part as a result of her close friendships with Carl Van Vechten and Thornton Wilder, both of whom having strong ties to Yale encouraged Stein to donate material to the Yale Collection of American Literature. Most pre-1946 gifts noted below were given by Stein through either Van Vechten or Wilder. The name of the go-between is given, if known.
1937 June Thornton Wilder, on behalf of Gertrude Stein, deposits typescripts of "Four in America," "An American and France," and "What are Masterpieces..."
1938 February-March Thornton Wilder, on behalf of Stein, deposits additional Stein works. One, "A Long Gay Book" is made a gift to the library following a formal letter from Stein to Andrew Keogh, Librarian of Yale University.
1939 July Deposit of typescripts of "Everybody's Autobiography" and "Stanzas in Meditation."
1940 April Deposit of part of the corrected galley proof of "Three Lives".
1940 November Carl Van Vechten gives all of his typescripts of Stein writings. These had been prepared by Toklas and sent to Van Vechten for safekeeping before the outbreak of World War II. Van Vechten also gives many of his own materials, such as photographs of Stein. (Letters to him from Stein, also given at this time, are considered part of Van Vechten's papers.)
1941 March 24 Following the success of an exhibition of Stein material at Yale, Stein writes Bernard Knollenberg, Librarian of Yale University, promising eventually to give additional manuscripts and letters at a future date.
1940 Friends of Stein begin to give material for a Gertrude Stein Collection.
1945-46 After long delays due to the war, Stein resumes correspondence with the Yale Library to plan the gift and transfer of the rest of her archive.
1946 July 23 Faced with the prospect of surgery, Stein writes her will, giving her writings to Yale University.
1946 July 27 Gertrude Stein dies in Paris.
1947 Shipments received at Yale from Alice Toklas of Stein material: manuscripts, books, photographs, and personal material.
1947-67 Alice Toklas sends intermittent additions for the Stein archive, principally posthumous appearances of Stein writings and clippings about Stein, along with letters bearing on Stein that Toklas received during this period.
1947-95 Friends and admirers of Stein and Toklas (especially Carl Van Vechten) continue to send material for the Stein Collection.
Because of the close association between Stein and Carl Van Vechten (he being her principal liaison with the Yale Library and later her literary executor), many items in the Stein/Toklas Papers were, in fact, given by Van Vechten. For years, donations from Van Vechten were integrated into this archive, creating a state in which it is difficult to distinguish the provenance of many items. Since his donations were given, in many cases, with Stein's knowledge or on her behalf, it has been decided that an attempt to extract the component of the archive actually given by Van Vechten would not be of benefit to researchers. The one notable exception to this decision is the determination that Stein's letters to Van Vechten are to remain in Van Vechten's papers.
In addition to the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers, there are two groups of closely connected materials in the Yale Collection of American Literature. The many items donated by friends and admirers during the years following Stein's death have been organized into the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Collection (YCAL MSS 77). Material from the estate of Leo Stein, combined with gifts from other parties, constitute the Leo Stein Collection (YCAL MSS 78). The finding aids for these collections describe their content and their relation to the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers consist of manuscripts, letters, photographs, printed materials, personal papers, and art and objects which document the life and work of Stein and Toklas, principally up until 1946, the year of Stein's death. The papers span the years 1837-1961.
The papers are housed in 173 boxes and consists of nine series: Writings, Correspondence of Gertrude Stein, Third party letters, Alice B. Toklas Correspondence, Personal Papers, Clippings, Photographs, Artworks, and Objects. Boxes 168-173 contain Oversize material and Restricted fragile papers.
Series I, Writings, (boxes 1-94) consists of five subseries: Gertrude Stein Bibliography, Unpublished Manuscripts and Fragments, Bound Volumes, Carnets, and Writings of Others. This series constitutes perhaps one of the best preserved, and most nearly complete, archives of a modern writer. Gertrude Stein made a commitment during her lifetime to ensure that her papers would be available for research and to this end she also took great care in organizing and preserving her manuscripts. In the Writings series, one will find ample evidence of Stein's focused output spanning five decades: her early innovative portrait style, the complex and interlocking hermetic writings of the 1920s, her move towards more public works, "real writing" as she called it, after the success of the Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas in the mid-1930s, and the reflective, even nostalgic works done towards the end of her life. While the bulk of the bibliography section documents the period from 1908, when Stein began to write consistently, to 1946, some of her earliest writings, done at Johns Hopkins and Radcliffe, can be found as well, either in printed form (Cultivated Motor Automatism, Box 10, folders 227-228) or as holographs (Daily Themes for English 22 at Radcliffe, Box 10, folders 238-239). The earliest independent works represented here are the first draft of what would become the Making of Americans, and the novel Q.E.D., both from around 1903. Texts are represented principally in two stages: manuscript notebooks and typescripts. A great many short pieces are accompanied by clippings of the versions printed in periodicals and newspapers.
The subseries Gertrude Stein Bibliography consists of writings by Stein recorded by bibliographers as having been published during Stein's lifetime or with the approval of Alice Toklas after Stein's death. These are listed alphabetically by title. The next section, Unpublished Manuscripts and Fragments, is listed alphabetically by incipit.
The fifteen Bound Volumes of typescripts which follow were received with Stein's papers in 1947 and were labeled by Stein as Volume 6 - Volume 20. They follow a chronological progression of texts from approximately 1908-1926. Cross-references have been made to these in the Gertrude Stein Bibliography. No evidence is extant of the existence of volumes 1-5, or any following volume 20.
A small group of Carnets, pocket-sized notebooks, also arrived with the archival material sent by Alice B. Toklas after Stein's death, although their significance as the earliest working notes for texts was not realized. Instead, they were classified by the library as personal effects. For many years, it was believed that Stein composed directly into notebooks. However, analysis of the existing carnets shows that, for Stein, the creation of texts was not simply a linear process. It is likely that ideas sprang from jottings in carnets, then were more fully developed in the holograph notebooks. After this, a typescript was made (usually with a carbon or two and usually by Alice B. Toklas). It can be supposed that there existed a great number of carnets (this observation is supported by notes in one carnet about the purchase of others), but only a few were received by the library.
At the end of this Series is a small group of Writing of Others, most notable among them, a draft of Sherwood Anderson's introduction to Stein's Geography and Plays.
The following information about Series I explains many of the technical aspects of the classification and arrangement of materials.
In keeping with Stein's unspecific approach to categories of texts, Writings have not been broken down into genres (such as plays and novels), nor has punctuation been used to indicate genres (e.g. quotation marks around titles of plays have not been added). However, other titles in the listing will be formatted according to standard practice; names of newspapers, for example, are underlined.
During the evolution from note form to full-fledged text, themes were often reiterated and broken off into several texts, making it difficult to see one text as truly distinct from another. In arranging and establishing titles for Stein writings, much work has been done to trace the often tangled origins of texts. Consideration has been given to the several Stein bibliographies in use for many decades by Stein scholars, but the use of an evident title assigned by Stein takes precedence over any subsequently assigned title. Cross-references have been made from commonly cited titles that do not match the established titles. Items which contain a single text will, of course, be listed under the established title. Items which contain more than one text (such as typescripts with several poems on a single page or a notebook with two plays) will be filed under the name of the first, or on occasion most significant, work in the item, with other contents appended in a note beginning "Also Contains:". Cross-references have been made for the other contents using the following format: Preciosilla Manuscript notebook [1913] In: Irma
"See:" and "See also:" references are used to establish references between variant titles and to Oversize housing for large items. In many lists of titles, the word "and" is capitalized ("AND") so that it will not be confused with a component part of a title.
Holograph manuscript originals are described as either "holograph manuscripts" for groups of individual loose sheets, or "manuscript notebook" for notebooks. Holographs and notebooks, due to their inherent nature as drafts, have not been described at any point as "corrected" In the case of multiple volumes, Stein's original numbering has been retained, even if this changes the numbering originally assigned by Donald Gallup. Very difficult groupings of volumes (e.g. Four in America), however, have been described using the Gallup sequence, but Stein's descriptions of each volume (e.g. "Wright vol. III") have been noted.
For typescripts, the following standard was followed: A version included in a bound volume (described by Gallup as "original typescript") has been deemed the primary typescript and has been described as "typescript." If a work does not appear in a bound volume, but there is a loose typescript which approximates the style of the bound volumes, this has been considered the primary typescript. All other typescripts are described as "typescript copy" - even if there are multiples. Typescripts given by Carl Van Vechten are often kept separate, but have in some instances been put with other typescript copies. All of these items are individually identified on the folder as having been given by Carl Van Vechten. If a typescript has substantive corrections, additions or deletions to the text, it has been described as "corrected". However, if the only change to a manuscript has been, in effect, to trace over faint letters or fill in the ending of a word that has trailed off the end of a carbon, these non-substantive corrections have not been described as "corrected." As evidenced by several items in the Stein/Toklas Collection, there may have been a number of carbons created from the original typescript, specifically intended to be sent to publishers. This would account for the lack of typescripts for certain texts.
As is standard practice for collections in the Beinecke Library, clippings which stand as evidence of the development of the writing process (printed versions of texts, reviews) have been filed along with the appropriate text drafts. This accounts for the appearance of many printed items in the Gertrude Stein Bibliography section of the Writings series which were previously filed with general clippings.
The Studies for the Making of Americans consist of various scraps and carnets which may have come as part of Stein's materials for this text or in a miscellaneous group. Most of the items were numbered in pencil by Leon Katz in the early 1960s. It is not clear if his numbering reflects the order of the final text or the state in which they were found. In the 1970s-80s, Ulla Dydo worked on the material and arranged the scraps and carnets in accordance with the sequence of the final manuscript text, but was not able to place all of the fragments numbered by Leon Katz or the unnumbered materials. These materials have been processed in the following order:
First group: numbered, assigned: Those items numbered by Katz and organized by Dydo. These are listed individually, with a brief physical description, an incipit and the original Katz number (e.g. Holograph leaf, "Begin with repetition about..." [#131] n.d.)
Second group: numbered, unassigned: These are the items numbered by Leon Katz that Ulla Dydo did not work on. There are divided into several folders with the numbers listed.
Third group: unnumbered, unassigned: Miscellaneous holograph pages and notebooks.
The section of Unpublished Manuscripts and Fragments contains materials previously filed in the various "Miscellaneous" or "Glass case" locations formerly assigned to the Stein archive. Notes or drafts which, upon careful examination, did correlate to a known Stein work, however, have been placed along with the other extant drafts. In the interest of not creating bibliographic "ghosts", the majority of the fragments and unidentified pieces have been left in this section. Those which could be identified as distinct entities have been individually foldered and identified with an incipit and document description (e.g. "A mes chers amis Gaston et Charlotte Chaboux...," holograph). Unidentified scraps and notes have been foldered at the end of this section and have been listed as "fragments".